Hope it held okay. Yes,
there. All right. בוקר טוב Boker tov
and ראש חודש, rosh chodesh, happy ראש חודש rosh chodesh everybody. Our
page is סנהדרין ל"ח. Sanhedrin lamed chet.
I kind of want to give a very brief intro which will
help frame where we are and that will help us understand why
we're having this conversation we're having. I also have a question but
don't shoot me. We all have questions. Exactly. No, my class is
different. Okay, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is five and a half lines. It
brings up things that then the בבלי Bavli will bring. Do you
want to see what's in it?
Yeah, five and a half lines.
No question. All right. All right, so we're going to mix and
match. Let me do my intro and then quick ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
then to סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. רגע. Rega. Okay. So we are in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin in פרק perek four, אחד דיני ממונות echad dinei mamonot and
we're talking about the ten differences between דיני ממונות dinei mamonot and
דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, monetary civil matters and capital. In the משנה
Mishna in the previous page we learned how to warn the witnesses
and we threatened them, we guilt tripped them, we explained them the
justice and righteousness why it's correct for them to say truth. And
now we're going to switch to אגדות aggadot about the place of
a human being in creation so we understand that if we're dealing
with life and death
what's the weight that is being placed on us when we're dealing
with the life of one human being. Okay. So very brief ירושלמי
Yerushalmi but I think most of the questions that will come up
here, I hope, will get answered as we go into the בבלי.
Bavli. So, in ירושלמי Yerushalmi we're on דף כ"ג ע"ב daf kaf
gimmel bet פרק ד' הלכה ט'. perek daled halacha tet. It looks
like this. It starts with the words כיצד מעומד keitzad me'umad and
it's five and a half lines in words at the end, sorry
my manuscript, it says אדם נברא בערב שבת. Adam nivra be'erev Shabbat.
Can I see what was that again? כ"ג ע"ב? kaf gimmel bet?
It looks like this except for the scribbles.
Okay. We're doing very briefly the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and then running into
the סנהדרין ל"ח. Sanhedrin lamed chet. רגע. Rega. All right.
אדם נברא בערב שבת, Adam nivra be'erev Shabbat, human, the human being,
Adam was created in the eve of שבת, Shabbat, Friday afternoon כדי
שיכנס תחילה למצוה kedei sheyikanes techila lemitzvah so he'll be able to
do a מצוה mitzvah immediately. That's one reason. דבר אחר, Davar acher,
another explanation, למה נברא באחרונה, lama nivra ba'achrona, why is he the
last creature to be created? משל למלך שעשה סעודה, Mashal lemelech she'asa
se'udah, this is parable to a king that made a meal. כשמתקין
הסעודה מזמין האורחים, Keshematkin hase'udah mazmin ha'orchim, the בבלי Bavli will expand
a little, when first he makes, he sets out the meal, then
invites the guests as opposed to letting the guests see the בלגן
balagan house while you're getting ready. כך, Kach, now they're bringing us
a פסוק pasuk from משלי, Mishlei, חכמות בנתה ביתה, chochmot banta beita,
and the פסוק pasuk in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is very broken up,
we'll see it in whole when we go to the בבלי. Bavli.
כך חכמות בנתה ביתה, Kach chochmot banta beita,
which I find interesting, especially in light of what's coming, that he
takes his example, God takes his example from a woman who builds
her house, who kind of institutes her house. That is the Holy
One Blessed Be He, הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu שבנה את
העולם, shebana et ha'olam, this is exactly like God who created the
world בחכמה, bechochma, with wisdom, שנאמר, shene'emar, and we're bringing a פסוק
pasuk from another source, בחכמה יסד ארץ וגו'. bechochma yasad aretz vego.
The continuation of the משלי Mishlei פסוק, pasuk, חצבה עמודיה שבעה, chatzva
amudeha shiva, she carved her pillars, שבעה, shiva, sorry, חצבה עמודיה שבעה,
chatzva amudeha shiva, אלו שבעת ימי בראשית, elu shivat yemei bereishit, these
are the seven days of creation. טבחה טבחה מסכה יינה, Tavcha tivcha
mascha yeina,
she gets the meat and mixes the wine, still continuing with משלי
Mishlei with Proverbs. This alludes to the ימים ונהרות, yamim veneharot, the
seas and the rivers וכל צרכי העולם, vechol tzorchei ha'olam, all the
needs of the
world. מי פתי יסור הנה, Mi peti yasur henna, when the phrase,
sorry, when the פסוק pasuk continues to ask מי פתי, mi peti,
who is a
fool, right?
Fool, but also somebody that can be influenced. Yes, that will come
here, that alludes to אדם וחוה. Adam veChava.
And then, and
then the ירושלמי Yerushalmi just stops and becomes even more cryptic and
it brings a פסוק pasuk that I think we saw yesterday in
ל"ז, lamed zayin, שמא תאמרו מה לנו ולצרה, shema tomru ma lanu
velatzara, and that is a פסוק pasuk that talks about us, possibly
asking or what do we need this trouble. If being a witness
is such a heavy load, maybe we shouldn't do it. כתיב, k'tiv,
they're bringing us a פסוק pasuk from מלכים, Melachim, we'll see it
in the context of the death of אחאב, Achav, who was the
king of ישראל. Yisrael. ויעבור הרינה במחנה. vaya'avor harina bamachane. מהו הרינה?
mahu harina? Now we have a discussion between,
and we know some of this discussion and we will see it,
whether God is joyful when an evildoer falls or not. רינה rina
from joy. וכך הוא אומר, v'kach hu omer, and then it contrasts
it with another verse from דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, from the, how
do you say דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, Chronicles, sorry, Chronicles, בצאת לפני
החלוץ. b'tzet lifnei hachalutz. And in that פסוק pasuk it says that
when they say...
מהו הרינה mahu harina
and then you said הריני? harini? הריני, harini, yeah, like the, my
joy, like השם's Hashem joy. But in the next verse, בצאת לפני
החלוץ, b'tzet lifnei hachalutz, it says הודו להשם כי טוב כי לעולם
חסדו. hodu la'Hashem ki tov ki l'olam chasdo. Like חסד chesed but
not טוב. tov. There's a tension there between what's going on and
the conclusion is ללמדך שאף מפלת הרשעים אינה שמחה לפני המקום. l'lamdecha
she'af mapalat ha'resha'im eina simcha lifnei ha'makom. To teach us that even
the downfall of the evildoers is not joyful for השם. Hashem. That's
interesting. We're going to take a deep breath, put this aside, and
now look at it much, much slower in the בבלי. Bavli.
That's helpful, and even up on top, הודו להשם,
hodu la'Hashem, we had before. Yes, but there's going to be the
tension and there's a few tensions that come in this פסוק, pasuk,
I in this דף. daf. I want to say that everyone that
I try to study with, online, offline, talks about how this דף,
daf, so I'm happy to teach, is so אגדתא agadata אגדתי. agadati.
אגדתא? agadata? אגדתי agadati
and so deep in its meanings that we can't definitely expect to
get into everything in forty-five minutes, but we'll at least view it
like we're going through an appetizer table and we're just picking and
choosing a few little bites from different things and give us an
idea of something to think about later. All right. We're starting from
three lines from the top on ל''ח, Lamed Chet, יהודה וחזקיה. Yehuda
v'Chizkiya.
And where we are there, if you remember yesterday at the bottom
of ל''ז, Lamed Zayin, we were talking about commentaries of the sons
of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya to the משנה Mishna that we had
in ל''ז א'. Lamed Zayin Aleph. So now we're going to continue
all these discussions that they had about the bloods, if you remember
yesterday, the bloods of קין, Kayin, of הבל Hevel calling and so
on. Now reminds us of another
beautiful,
interesting story that involves the sons of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Beginning.
יהודה וחזקיה בני רבי חייא הוו יתבי בסעודתא קמיה דרבי. Yehuda v'Chizkiya
b'nei Rabbi Chiya havu yatvei b'seudata kamei d'Rabbi. So יהודה וחזקיה, Yehuda
v'Chizkiya,
we're on the third line top of ל''ח, Lamed Chet, now fourth,
the sons of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, were sitting in a meal
before רבי. Rabbi. ולא הוו קאמרי ולא מידי. v'lo havu kaamrei v'lo
midi. They didn't say a word and no nothing, didn't speak of
anything. אמר להו, amar lehu, רבי Rabbi says to his servants, אשקוהו
חמרא לדרדקי. ashkuhu chamra l'dardakei. Increase the wine for the lads, for
these young people. כי היכי דלימרו מילתא. ki heichi d'limru milta. I
want to hear what they have to say, and as we'll see,
wine increases fluidity in speech.
כיון דאיבסום, keivan d'ivsum, because they became inebriated, פתחו ואמרו. patchu v'amru.
Now here is their teaching.
אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו שני בתי אבות מישראל. ein Ben
David ba ad she'yichlu shnei batei avot mi'Yisrael. ואלו הן v'elu hen
ראש גולה שבבבל ונשיא שבארץ ישראל. resh gola she'be'Bavel v'nasi she'be'Eretz Yisrael.
I will translate.
They give a teaching they probably need more wine.
Yeah, they maybe want to think again why they gave them more
wine. And what they say, and they'll bring us immediately a פסוק
pasuk from ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. What they say, the משיח Mashiach will not
come until two institutions will cease from the people of ישראל. Yisrael.
One is the head of the גולה, gola, and the other one
is the נשיא nasi in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now who's the
נשיא nasi in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? רבי Rabbi in front of
whom they're sitting. So kind of picture this situation with these two
young scholars, their dad, the נשיא, nasi, the servants, they get the
wine and that's what they say. And he quotes a פסוק pasuk
from ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, and the
פסוק pasuk says: והיה למקדש ולאבן נגף ולצור מכשול לשני בתי ישראל.
v'haya l'mikdash u'l'even negef u'l'tzur michshol l'shnei batei Yisrael. The פסוק pasuk
says there's going to be a מקדש, mikdash, but also it's going
to be the מקדש mikdash is going to be... Like a stumbling
block and a stumbling rock. Like these are kind of parable, אבן
נגף *even negef*, something that makes you trip, ולצור מכשול *ve-ltzur michshol*,
we know from לא תשים מכשול *lo tasim michshol*, don't put a
stumbling block, לשני בתי ישראל Yisrael *lishnei batei Yisrael*. You can see
if you have it on the side, this is from ישעיהו Yeshayahu
*Yeshayahu* ח *Chet*. So, רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya* is going to avoid
the conversation about it, but I think this is super interesting because
we in essence have a tension between our waiting for the משיח
Mashiach *Mashiach* and between the current institutions that run our community in
place. As long as these are in existence, the משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*
cannot come. It's like his job is taken. But we can't give
up what we have.
It
brought to mind this Israeli movie that came out just like maybe
six months ago that's called לעבור את הקיר *La'avor et haKir*. In
English it's called The Wedding Plan. It's about a girl, she's 32
years old, she's been to countless dates in the last 10, 12
years and she says, that's it, I'm done, I'm getting married. I'm
going to get the hall, the flowers, the dress, the catering, everything.
And everybody says to her, what about the groom? And she says
in Hebrew, קטן על השם Hashem להביא לי חתן *Katan al Hashem
lehavi li chatan*. Like it's a small thing for God to bring
me a groom. I'm going to take care of everything else, what
is the problem? All he needs to do is bring the guy.
And the community very interestingly says to her, you can't count on
miracles, you can't operate like this. And she says, but we believe
that השם Hashem *Hashem* can do anything. And we'll see later in
our דף daf *daf* that it says, maybe it was even yesterday,
that it says בשבילי נברא העולם *Bishvili nivra ha-olam*, right? The world
was created for me. So what do you mean this can't happen?
It can happen. But that tension between, you know, what we do...
people say if you believe in your prayer, then on שמיני עצרת
*Shmini Atzeret* go with a raincoat to שול *shul*, right? So it's
like we do things and yet do we believe in them? And
רבי *Rebbi* it strikes him too, sorry for the digression, strikes him
too here very much and he says, and there's a question whether
this is a question or a statement, he says to them, רבי
*Rebbi* to the sons, אמר להם Amar lahem: *amar lahem*, בני *banai*,
could be read like this: קוצים אתם מטילים לי בין עיני *kotzim
atem matilin li bein einai*, you are throwing thorns in my eyes.
Or, בני *banai*, קוצים אתם מטילים לי בין עיני *kotzim atem matilin
li bein einai*? Like are you intending to throw thorns, are you
intending to harm me? אמר לו רבי חייא *Amar lo Rabbi Chiya*,
רבי *Rebbi*, אל ירע בעיניך *al yera be-eineicha*, ייין *yayin* ניתן בשבעים
אותיות *nitan be-shiv'im otiyot* וסוד *ve-sod* ניתן בשבעים אותיות *nitan be-shiv'im otiyot*.
I'll translate in a minute. נכנס יין יצא סוד *Nichnas yayin yatza
sod*. Famous line. רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya* says to רבי *Rebbi*, don't
be upset, you gave them wine. The גימטריה gematria *gematria* of wine,
we will put this somewhere where people can see, יוד *yud*, יוד
*yud*, 10 and 10, נון *nun*, 50, 70. סוד *sod*, סמך
*samech* is 60, וו *vav* is 6, דלת *dalet* is 4, also
70. So it's a little bit like for me it's an image
as if there's a pipe with the secrets inside, and when the
wine comes in, it pushes the secrets out, as if there's no
room for both of them together in that little pipe. Okay. So
now this reminds us of another shaping.
You mean in fact it's your fault, you gave them wine?
A little bit. You pushed it out of them, so that's the
teaching that they brought, which I think just strengthens the validity of
the teaching because he doesn't argue the teaching, right? He just tries
to back up his kids.
He uses the סוד *sod* of the סוד *sod*. Right. Wine has
truth to it.
It has truth to it. Yes, he doesn't argue the statement. He
just... okay. Rushing along. אמר רב Rav חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda* אמר
מר עוקבא *amar Mar Ukva*, ואמרי לה *ve-amrei lah* אמר רב חסדא
*amar Rav Chisda* דרש מרי בר מר *darash Mari bar Mar*. So
unclear who's this statement by, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* got it from
מר עוקבא *Mar Ukva* or from מרי בר מר *Mari bar Mar*.
מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv *Mai d'chtiv*, what is this פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*
that we have a hard time understanding? וישקד השם Hashem, על הרעה
ויביאה עלינו כי צדיק השם Hashem, אלוהינו *Vayishkod Hashem al hara'ah vayevi'eha
aleinu ki tzaddik Hashem Elokeinu*. משום דצדיק השם Hashem וישקד השם Hashem
על הרעה ויביאה עלינו *Mishum de-tzaddik Hashem vayishkod Hashem al hara'ah vayevi'eha
aleinu*? The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is saying, and we see it in
דניאל *Daniel*, that God is diligent, studious, and brings evil on us
because he's righteous. So again we're presented with a crazy tension. God
is righteous, therefore he hastens evil things to happen to us? Is
that really possible? asks the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. משום שצדיק השם Hashem
*Mishum she-tzaddik Hashem*? And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* answers אין *in*, yes.
And they'll give us a couple of examples.
God did us a favor, He did us righteousness with the Jewish
people that he
before the diaspora of צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu already the exile, sorry, not diaspora,
exile better, already the exile of יכניה Yechanya happened. So what's the
situation just very briefly? This is the time of the first בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash and in the destruction of the first בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, it's not all at once. There were three גלויות galuyot
until the final one. What we see here is that they're in
stages. יכניה Yechanya was a king of Israel, he was exiled first
by the, what's called, Neo-Babylonians, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and his army. צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu
was placed to be king after him in יהודה Yehuda and some
time later צדקיהו was exiled as well. That means that the second
exile, when they came to בבל, Bavel, there were already the first
exiles there. How do we learn this? There is a
פסוק, pasuk דכתיב ביה בגלות יכניה, dechtiv bei begalut Yechanya, החרש והמסגר
אלף. Hecharash Vehamasger elef. So על פניו, al panav, like simple פשט,
pshat, this פסוק pasuk, says חרש charash is a craftsman, מסגר masger
is a smith, like somebody that works on the locks of the
city. There were thousands of them already in בבל. Bavel. The גמרא
Gemara is going to open this up. חרש Charash is the same
שורש shoresh like the word חרש, cheresh, deaf. כיוון שפותחין הכל נעשו
כחרשין. keivan shepotchin hakol na'asu kechershin. This is a group that is
so learned in תורה Torah that when they open a תורה Torah
text, everyone around them becomes quiet like mute deaf people that don't
have anything to say. מסגר, Masger,
which could be smith, but here they're playing on the שורש shoresh
סגור, sagur, closed. כיוון שסוגרין בהלכה שוב אין פותחין. keivan shesogrin bahalacha
shuv ein potchin. They were so knowledgeable that when they closed a
halachic matter, nobody could open it. And how many were they? כמה
היו? kama hayu? אלף. Elef. So it was like a substantial amount,
a welcome committee for the next exile.
עולא Ulla is going to bring us another example, if you remember,
we're talking about how God's evil actions give us צדקה, tzedaka,
do us the favor.
It's a super hard concept and people take it to the extent
of whatever, so the Holocaust had something good. I don't want to
go all the way there. I don't want to do. Right, exactly.
It's good as a philosophy, it's very painful when it's close to
home. I don't want to go all the way
there. Give me. Okay. Yes.
This also sort of
has indicating about the origin story of יהודי בבל, Yehudei Bavel, they
were already so learned in the greatness of
בבל.
Bavel. Some of the learned people were already there.
And also comes back later with the problems that עזרא Ezra and
נחמיה Nechemia had when they came back to the land, the Jewish
people that stayed there
sort of showed the superiority of בבל Bavel maybe.
Could be, very much could be. Okay, עולא Ulla gives us another
גימטריה which is going to complicate our life. And עולא Ulla says
here is another place where השם's Hashem kind of what we perceive
as evil doing was good. עולא אמר, Ulla amar, he said, שהקדים
שתי שנים לונושנתם. shehikdim shtei shanim lenoshantem.
Okay,
so check out this word ונושנתם. venoshantem.
And trust me, but we could calculate. ת Tav is 400, ש
Shin is 300,
another 100, the total here is 852.
Okay, the understanding is that, what does it mean שהקדים שתי שנים
לונושנתם? shehikdim shtei shanim lenoshantem?
That the people of Israel were in the land of Israel 850
years. Why? Look on the side if you have it in your
גמרא. Gemara This פסוק pasuk is from דברים. Devarim. And the continuation
of that פסוק, pasuk if you want to look it up,
because of this, because ונושנתם, venoshantem, the next פסוק pasuk is, if
you do this, i.e., for the Rabbis, if you stay there 852
years and then you do bad things, ואבדתם, va'avadetem, you will be
lost. So according to עולא, Ulla, what does השם Hashem do? He
subtracts our years so that the rest of the פסוק pasuk, can't
come true. So we're only in the land 850 years. Lengthy discussions
how exactly are these 850 years calculated, are they with מצרים, Mitzrayim,
without, with the 40 years in the desert, without, who's in, who's
out, not going there.
So this is entirely in years down as if you didn't get
out of Egypt by the
50th year, like 49 and then the 50th, right, right, right. So
this is maybe similar in the sense that if we fulfilled the
852 years, we would not be able to go. Now another word
in the next פסוק pasuk is אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar
Rav Acha bar Yaakov, שמע מינה מהרה. Shma Mina Mehera. In the
next פסוק, pasuk the word מהר, maher, quick, is mentioned. So what
do they understand? דמרי עלמא, De-mareh alma, תמני מאה וחמישים ותרתין הוו.
tmani me'ah ve-chamishin ve-tarten havo. For השם, Hashem
852 is quick.
Well, כי אלף שנים בעיניך
כיום אתמול.
ki eleph shanim be-eynecha
ke-yom etmol.
So for השם, Hashem 852 years is quickly next time we want
something, then figure out this might happen in 852 years and it's
going to be quick. There's a great fun movie, old, George Burns
playing God, Oh God, and God says to him, when I got
up this morning, Albert Einstein was still in grade school. So it's
along these lines. Sorry for leaving. Okay. We're picking up back from
the משנה mishna on ל"ז. lamed zayin. לפיכך נברא אדם יחידי Lefikach
nivra adam yechidi and let's see some מדרשים midrashim and explanations
about it. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, the rabbis taught in the
ברייתא. baraita. אדם יחידי נברא. Adam yechidi nivra. The human being was
created a single one, only one. מפני מה? Mifnei mah? Why? שלא
יהיו המינים אומרים, she-lo yehu ha-minim omrim, let not the אפיקורסים apikorsim
say, הרבה רשויות בשמים, harbeh rashuyot ba-shamayim, there are a lot of
entities in the heaven. דבר אחר, Davar acher, מפני הצדיקים ומפני הרשעים.
mifnei ha-tzadikim u-mifnei ha-reshaim. I'm going to do this really fast because
of the time, but hopefully still clear. Okay. Another explanation
is that because of the righteous and the evildoers. שלא יהיו הצדיקים
אומרים, she-lo yehu ha-tzadikim omrim, אנו בני צדיק, anu bnei tzadik, ורשעים
אומרים, ve-reshaim omrim, אנו בני רשע. anu bnei rasha. So the righteous
and the evil people will not say, oh, we're the children of
the righteous, and the evil people will say, oh, we're the children
of the evil. דבר אחר, Davar acher, another explanation. מפני המשפחות, Mifnei
ha-mishpachot, because of the families. שלא יהיו משפחות מתגרות זו בזו. she-lo
yehu mishpachot mitgarot zo be-zo. So families would not like tease each
other. ומה עכשיו שנברא יחיד מתגרות, u-mah achshav she-nivra yachid mitgarot, נבראו
שנים, nivra'u shnayim, על אחת כמה וכמה. al achat kamah ve-chamah. Even
now that he was created a single entity, the families are fighting,
teasing each other. If they were two of them, all the more
so.
דבר אחר, Davar acher, מפני הגזלנים ומפני
החמסנים. mifnei ha-gazlanim u-mifnei ha-chamsanim. ומה עכשיו שנברא יחידי, u-mah achshav she-nivra
yechidi, גוזלין וחומסין, gozlin ve-chomsin, נבראו שנים, nivru shnayim, על אחת כמה
וכמה. al achat kamah ve-chamah. Same kind of idea because of the
thieves and robbers. And now he was created single, people still steal
from each other, it's like we're stealing from ourselves, right, in this
sense. If there were two, all the more so. So these are
all reasons that are great, but they all have to do with
how beneficial it is for us, to the humans. Now there's another
side to this coin, you'll see in a minute. ולהגיד גדולתו u-lehagid
gdulato
and to proclaim the greatness of God. So not for our benefit,
but for God's benefit. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, was taught. להגיד גדולתו
של מלך מלכי המלכים הקדוש ברוך הוא, le-hagid gdulato shel melech malchei
ha-mlachim ha-kadosh baruch hu, in order to proclaim the greatness of the
King of kings, הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, the Holy One,
Blessed be He. שאדם טובע כמה מטבעות בחותם אחד וכולם דומים זה
לזה. she-adam toveia kamah matbe'ot be-chotam echad ve-kulam domim zeh la-zeh. A
human being mints coins in the same stamp and they all look
alike. אבל הקדוש ברוך הוא טובע כל אדם בחותמו של אדם הראשון
ואין אחד מהם דומה לחברו. aval hakadosh baruch hu toveia kol adam
be-chotamo shel adam ha-rishon ve-ein echad me-hem domeh le-chavero. הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, Holy One, Blessed be He, makes a human, all
come out from אדם, Adam, and yet we all look different. And
prooftext from איוב, Iyov, of all places to bring a prooftext for,
right? תתהפך כחומר חותם ויתייצבו כמו
לבוש. titehafech ke-chomer chotam ve-yityatzvu kmo levush. So the material turns and
changes like a stamp and yet everyone is dressed, ויתייצבו כמו לבוש,
ve-yityatzvu kmo levush, they have a different clothing on them, they have
a different outside on them. Okay. ומפני מה אין פרצופין דומים זה
לזה? u-mifnei mah ein partzufin domim zeh la-zeh? What is the reason
that our faces don't all look alike? Like for השם it would
have been no problem to make our faces all look exactly identical.
שלא יראה אדם דירה נאה ואשה נאה ויאמר שלי. she-lo yireh adam
dirah na'ah ve-ishah na'ah ve-yomar sheli. So a person will not walk
around and say, oh, nice apartment, nice woman, those are mine, because
they all look alike. Now, of course, question I haven't found an
answer is, if we all look alike, how do you know that
the woman is beautiful, right? Everybody has to be looking alike. But
I will not go there.
Okay. שנאמר she-ne'emar as it is said. His light from the evil
doers and makes sure that like the world is set up in
a way that they will not succeed. תניא. Tanya. היה רבי מאיר
אומר, Haya Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would teach. בשלושה
דברים אדם משתנה בחברו. Bishlosha devarim adam nishtaneh bachavero. There are three
major things things that a person is different from his friend. בקול
במראה ובדעת, bekol bemareh uv'daat, in his voice, in his looks, and
in his brain, in his wisdom or knowledge. Wisdom is not so
good. Knowledge, better.
Thinking, mind, thinking, yes.
בקול ובמראה משום ערווה. bekol uv'mareh mishum ervah.
Voice and looks are different so that people will not come to
immorality so that they will, it's like I think רש"י Rashi said,
at night they'll be able to hear the different voice of their
spouse, in the day they'll be able to see and they won't
mix up people and take the wrong person.
ובדעת מפני הגזלנים והחמסנים, uv'daat mipnei hagazlanim vehachamsanim, and again רש"י Rashi
explains that because we have different ways of thinking then each one
of us will hide their goods in a different way and we
won't be able to read each other's minds, which I think is
important. Disappointing but important that our ability to read each other's minds
is limited. All right. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אדם נברא בערב שבת,
Adam nivra b'erev shabbat, and this is what we saw in the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ומפני מה? U'mipnei mah? שלא יהיו המינים אומרים, Shelo yihyu
haminim omrim, שותף היה לו להקדוש ברוך הוא במעשה בראשית. shuttaf haya
lo l'hakadosh baruch hu b'maaseh bereishit.
God made sure to create אדם Adam the very last
creation so the Epicureans wouldn't say, "Oh yeah, God had a partner
in creation," i.e. there were two. דבר אחר, Davar acher, another matter.
שאם תזוח דעתו עליו, she'im tazooach daato alav, אומר לו, omer lo,
יתוש קדמך במעשה בראשית. yatush k'damcha b'maaseh bereishit. If אדם Adam
become becomes זחוח, zachuach, becomes too self-haughty, self-confident, thinking himself he's who
knows what, then God can say to him, "What are you making
such a big deal out of self yourself? Even a mosquito came
before you in time of creation." דבר אחר, Davar acher, that's what
we saw in ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, כדי שיכנס למצווה מיד, k'dei sheyikanes l'mitzvah
miyad, so he will immediately
be able to do a מצווה. mitzvah. רש"י Rashi says שבת, Shabbat,
I think okay
good. דבר אחר, Davar acher, we saw this too. כדי שיכנס לסעודה
מיד, k'dei sheyikanes l'seudah miyad, so he will immediately be
part of a of a meal, i.e. that he will find everything
ready. And now we see the משל, mashal, the parable that we
saw in ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, a little bit more expanded. משל למלך בשר
ודם, mashal l'melech basar vadam, like a human king, שבנה פלטרין ושכללן
והתקין סעודה. she'bana paltarin v'shichl'lan v'hitkin seudah. The king built a palace,
improved it, and put out a meal. ואחר כך הכניס אורחים, v'achar
kach hichnis orchim, only then he brings the guests. שנאמר, shenemar, here's
a פסוק pasuk from משלי, Mishlei, we will see the whole פסוק
pasuk and then break it up. חכמות בנתה ביתה חצבה עמודיה שבעה.
chochmot banta beita chatzva amudeiha shiva. So with wisdom she built her
house, she carved her pillars seven, seven pillars. טבחה טבחה מסכה
יינה, tavcha tivcha mascha yeina, she gets the meat, slaughters the meat
and mixes the wine. אף ערכה שולחנה, af archa shulchana, she sets
the table. ושלחה נערותיה תקרא על גפי מרומי קרת, v'shalcha naaroteiha tikra
al gappei meromei karet, she sends her girls and she calls from
on high of the city. This is our the like three consecutive
פסוקים psukim in משלי, Mishlei, and now we're we're going to break
them up. I like this for the record that השם learned how
to create the world from the woman in משלי. Mishlei. Just saying.
Okay. חכמות, Chochmot, now we'll see that it backfires, so not yet
extremely excited but at least it's there. Okay. חכמות בנתה ביתה, chochmot
banta beita, the wisdom that she built her house, זו מידתו של
הקדוש ברוך הוא שבנה את כל העולם כולו בחכמה. zu midato shel
hakadosh baruch hu shebana et kol haolam kulo b'chochma. Again we saw
the very very cryptic version of it in ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. That's the
wisdom eludes to the wisdom with which God created the whole world.
חצבה עמודיה שבעה, chatzva amudeiha shiva,
she carved her pillars seven. אלו שבעה ימי בראשית. elu shiva yemei
bereishit. These are the seven days of creation. טבחה טבחה מסכה יינה,
tavcha tivcha mascha yeina,
the preparing the meal and the wine. אף ערכה שולחנה, af archa
shulchana, setting the table. אלו ימים ונהרות וכל צורכי העולם. elu yamim
v'neharot v'chol tzorchei haolam. So the meal and preparing the table are
all the things that are you know on the layer of the
world. שלחה נערותיה תקרא, shalcha naaroteiha tikra, זה אדם וחוה, zeh Adam
v'Chava, when she sends her girls to call like for the guest,
that is inviting אדם וחוה Adam v'Chava to come. על גפי מרומי
קרת. al gappei meromei karet. The end of the sentence, from on
high of the city.
רבה בר חנה Rabba bar Chana challenges this statement.
רבה בר חנה Rabba bar Chana אמר מכדי כתיב amar michdi ktiv
על גבי al gabei וכתיב u'ktiv על כסא. al kisse. We have
a contradiction between two פסוקים psukim in the משלי. Mishlei. In one
of them it says it was on high and on the other
one it says it was on the seat, on the chair. So
which one is it? Was it on high or was it on
the chair?
Not a problem, the גמרא Gemara settles it. בתחילה batchila על גבי
al gabei ולבסוף u'levasof על כסא. al kisse. Initially אדם Adam was
on high but later he was on the chair. What is the
chair? Some say that this is the like his wedding seat when
he gets Eve. Okay, immediate problem. They bring in us a פסוק
pasuk that says מי פתי יסור הנה חסר לב. mi peti yasur
henna chasar lev. The introduction of Eve to the life of חוה,
Chava, the woman to the life of אדם Adam
inspires, evokes a פסוק pasuk that says who is the foolish is
a little bit strong, but like the the one that's being tempted,
right, the one that's being alluded that will come here, he lacks
a heart. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, Holy One
blessed be He said, who tempted him this one? אשה אמרה לו,
isha amrah lo, the woman told him. And now another פסוק pasuk
that says the נואף, noef, the adulterer is חסר לב chasar lev
is somebody who is lacking a heart like lacking understanding and that
is kind of compared with אדם. Adam. Hard to understand this little
section, for the sake of time we will leave it. Okay, תניא.
Tanya. אמר רבי מאיר, amar Rabbi Meir, תניא. Tanya. היה רבי מאיר
אומר, haya Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say,
אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon מכל העולם כולו הוצבר עפרו. mi'kol ha'olam kulo
hutzbar afaro. I really like this imagery that אדם Adam shares his
name with the word אדמה, adamah, with the word earth, right? And
here the גמרא Gemara suggests to us that אדם Adam was created
like his his dirt, right, his materials was made from dust from
all over the world. שנאמר shene'emar גלמי ראו עיניך, golmi rau enecha,
like my raw material you see. Because in parentheses my גמרא Gemara
says כי ה' עיניו משוטטות בכל הארץ. ki Hashem einav meshotetot bechol
ha'aretz. God looks all over the world and from like the choicest
place he took the raw material to create אדם's Adam's body. אמר
רב אושעיה משמיה דרב,
amar Rav Oshaya
mishmei de'Rav, אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon גופו מבבל gufo mi'Bavel
וראשו מארץ ישראל verosho me'Eretz Yisrael ואיבריו משאר הארצות, ve'eivarav mi'shear ha'aratzot,
עגבותיו agvotav אמר רב אחא amar Rav Acha מאקרא דאגמא. me'Akra d'Agma.
Okay, so we the human being is created from stuff from all
over the world. This definitely speaks to me. Okay. The body's in
one place and the head and heart is somewhere else. Okay. So
he says the body is from בבל Bavel
and the head, look at רש"י Rashi saying from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael שהיא גבוהה וחשובה מכל הארצות. she'hi gvohah vechashuva mikol ha'aratzot. This
maybe David speaks to your tension between or like the tension between
בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So fine, the body is
from בבל, Bavel, right, like the materialistic thing, but the ראש rosh
is from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael which is higher from כל הארצות.
kol ha'aratzot. איבריו, eivarav, his hands and limbs are from all over
the world.
עגבותיו, agvotav, his buttocks are from אקרא דאגמא, Akra d'Agma, one of
the lakes which is in בבל Bavel and as we've seen them
elsewhere was other stories. Okay. אמר רבי
יוחנן בר חנינא amar Rabbi Yochanan bar Chanina שתים עשרה שעות הוי
היום. shtem-esrei sha'ot havei hayom.
Does this include the story about אדם Adam being able to see
from one end...
you we will see that he's big the whole world this way
and that.
So this idea that his dust was taken from the entire world
you know as it says ה' Hashem's his eyes swept over the
entire earth, ה' Hashem's eyes, and then אדם Adam has that quality
before before the sin, right?
This this really like deserves a whole course just this דף daf
on what the גמרא Gemara teaches us about the human being, his
or her one let's say one's greatness and also one's smallness and
how we supposed to hold all these things all at the same
time which is whatever kind of what make what makes life and
what breaks life right what makes it amazing and what makes it
crazy or impossible.
Yes, the short answer is yes. Alright. שתים
עשרה שעות הוי היום. shtem-esrei sha'ot havei hayom. The first day. Now
let's see how this first day of Adam's life, Adam's creation was
divided. שעה ראשונה sha'ah rishonah first hour. שעה ראשונה sha'ah rishonah first
hour,
הוצבר עפרו. hutzbar afaro. In the first hour the dust was collected.
שניה נעשה גולם. shnia na'asa golem. Golem is like the stage before
the butterfly flies out, like he becomes, what do you call it,
there's a scientific word for it, he becomes this butterfly, a cocoon
kind of. Yeah, there's a word. Three is like he's like the
dough. He has the yeast but nothing yet has happened, right? We
collected all the raw material, we made it into a ball. שלישית
נמתחו איבריו. shlishis nimtechu evarav. In the third hour his limbs stretched
out. רביעית נזרקה בו נשמה. revi'is nizreka bo neshama. In the fourth
hour the soul was the soul, sorry, the soul
was kind of shot into him.
מזרק mazrek in modern Hebrew is a syringe, right? So it was
like shot into him, thrown into him. חמישית עמד על רגליו. chamishis
amad al raglav. In the fifth hour he stood on his legs.
שישית קרא שמות. shishis kara shemos. In the sixth hour he named
the animals. שביעית נזדווגה לו חוה. shvi'is nizdavga lo chava. In the
seventh hour he got the woman. שמינית עלו למטה שנים וירדו ארבעה.
shminis alu lamita shnayim veyardu arba'ah. So there is an understanding
that in the eighth hour they were, they started out as two,
Adam and חוה, Chava, and then they became four. Some say Kayin
had a sister, some say Kayin and Hevel. תשיעית נצטווה שלא לאכול
מן האילן. tshi'is nitztave shelo l'echol min ha'ilan. On the ninth hour
he was commanded not to eat from the tree. עשירית סרח. asiris
sarach. In the tenth hour he sinned. אחת עשרה נידון. achas esreh
nidon. On the eleventh hour his sentence was pronounced. שתים עשרה נטרד
והלך לו. shtaim esre nitrad vehalach lo. On the twelfth hour he
was kicked
out. שנאמר shenemar אדם ביקרו בל ילין. adam bikaro bal yalin. It's
said, I think it's תהלים, Tehillim, yes, that אדם, adam, it could
be אדם adam just a generic human being, but in this sense
they're saying אדם, adam, like this Adam, ביקרו בל ילין. bikaro bal
yalin. He did not sleep, he was not לן lan in the
place of glory, like which means in the Garden of Eden. So
he did not even get to sleep one night in the Garden
of Eden.
I think it's על המיטה? al hamita? עלו המיטה? alu hamita?
Where are we?
עלו למיטה, alu lemita, got it, got it, got it. Okay. So
like they went to bed. They went to bed two, better, went
to bed two
and came back four. That's quick.
They say it was Kayin and his twin sister.
Yeah, that's what they say, yeah, yeah, yeah, that Kayin had a
sister. Okay.
אמר רמי בר חמא. amar Rami bar Chama. אין חיה רעה שולטת
באדם אלא אם כן נדמה לו כבהמה. ein chaya ra'ah sholetes ba'adam
ela im kein nidmeh lo kebeheima.
There's no an evil animal can't have control over human unless he,
it seems to him, the human being seems as an animal. Like
again, something that we can discuss in length.
There's a lot of מדרשים midrashim not here, although it will be
mentioned, about this פסוק pasuk where Hashem says נעשה אדם, na'aseh adam,
right? Who is it that is this נעשה, na'aseh, who's the plural?
So the classic Rashi is that it's the angels, פמליא של מעלה,
pamalia shel ma'ala, that he consults the angels on high to let
us make man. But there's also a מדרש midrash that's really the
פשט pshat that's amazing, that God talks to the animals. They were
around. And he says to the animals, let us, me and you,
God and animals, let us make man. And so man is got
this animalistic side to him along with divine spiritual, and here it
says to us
this
does not come across unless that is what the person, whatever, gives
out. שנאמר shenemar נמשל כבהמות נדמו. nimshal kebeheimos nidmu. That we will
be seen as animals. Okay, we have a
mnemonic. Tongue twister.
Okay.
But that, it will become semi-obvious. I don't know how much of
this page becomes obvious, but as obvious as it gets. So we
had שעה, sha'ah, בסוף, basof, ונרמי. v'Narmi. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. בשעה שביקש הקדוש ברוך הוא לבראות את
האדם, besha'ah shebikaish Hakadosh Baruch Hu livros es ha'adam, ברא כת אחת
של מלאכי השרת. bara kas achas shel malachei hasharais. When God had
in his mind to create the human being, he also created a
group of the ministering angels. created one group, one sect of angels.
אמר להם: Amar lahem: רצונכם נעשה אדם בצלמנו? retzonchem na'aseh adam betzalmenu?
Would you like us to make man in our image? אמרו לפניו,
Amru lefanav, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, מה מעשיו? ma ma'asav?
They wanted to know before they commit to this creation activity. What
is he doing, what is his activities? אמר להם: Amar lahem: כך
וכך מעשיו. kach vechach ma'asav. So he told them what human beings
do. אמרו לפניו, Amru lefanav, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, מה
אנוש כי תזכרנו ובן אדם כי תפקדנו? ma enosh ki tizkerenu uven
adam ki tifkedenu? Question mark or exclamation mark.
They said to him, Holy One Blessed be He, what are you
mindful? Why are you bringing this creature into the world? Right? What
are you doing bringing him here?
הושיט אצבע קטנה ביניהם ושרפם. Hoshit etzba ktana beinehem vesrafam. He singed
them basically and they just poof'd away, these angels. וכן כת שניה.
Vechen kat shniya. This is also what happened to the second sect
of angels. כת שלישית, Kat shlishit, אמרו לפניו: amru lefanav: ריבונו של
עולם, Ribono shel olam, ראשונים שאמרו לפניך מה הועילו? rishonim she'amru lefanecha
ma ho'ilu? The third time he created this sect of angels, they
said: Holy One Blessed be He, the first ones that you asked
for their opinion, what good was that? We don't want to go
the same route. כל העולם כולו שלך הוא. Kol ha'olam kulo shelcha
hu. כל מה שאתה רוצה לעשות בעולמך עשה. Kol ma she'ata rotze
la'asot be'olamcha asei. This whole world is yours. Whatever you want to
do, do it. So God created
man. כיוון שהגיע לאנשי דור המבול ואנשי דור הפלגה שמעשיהם מקולקלים, kevan
shehiga le'anshei dor hamabul ve'anshei dor haplaga shema'aseihem mekulkalim, אמרו לפניו: amru
lefanav: ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, לא יפה אמרו ראשונים לפניך?
lo yafe amru rishonim lefanecha? When the world proceeded to the generation
of the flood and the generation of the Tower of Babel, of
dispersionment, yes, that their actions are spoiled or ruined,
they said to him: We told you so God, wasn't the right,
weren't the early ones correct before you? אמר להם: ועד זקנה אני
הוא ועד שיבה אני אסבול. ve'ad zikna ani hu ve'ad seiva ani
esbol. So Hashem quotes to them a פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו that
says, basically he says to them, listen, I was here first, I
will be here last, until the end of time, until old age,
I am the one that will carry the world. I know what
I'm doing. This is what's going, this is the way it's going
to go. Again, could use a whole course just to go into
all these ideas. What does it mean that God is there עד
זקנה, ad zikna, so not beyond, like until old, but not beyond?
Or anyway, every one of these words needs help and our salad
bar we will not have a full meal. Okay.
It could be that old age could be the man, man's old
age.
Not obviously could perceive it, yeah, yeah, yeah, but like but God
says to the angels: ועד זקנה אני הוא. ve'ad zikna ani hu.
So maybe also can be understood that he's the one that will
be there with man until man's old age as a humanity, that
God will be there to the end of time with humanity, so
he kind of he knows what he's doing. One way or another,
he pushes the angels back, which
theologically, philosophically, like he creates the angels in order to consult them
in order to then push them away. So it's like, we need
both these things. If we say he can't do it, God can't
create angels, we just minimize them, but now we also limit them
on the other side, right? How do we do, how do we
do both, right?
Like it's just for the decision making, you have committees or...
right,
so that's how we were created by a committee, that explains everything.
Okay. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. Rav Yehuda says
in the name of Rav. אדם הראשון מסוף העולם ועד סופו היה.
Adam HaRishon misof ha'olam ve'ad sofo haya. The first human was so
big he was from the beginning of the world to its end.
שנאמר: Shene'emar: למן היום אשר ברא אלוהים אדם על הארץ ולמקצה השמים
ועד קצה השמים. lemin hayom asher bara Elohim adam al ha'aretz ulimiktze
hashamayim ve'ad ktze hashamayim. Because we have a פסוק pasuk that says
in Deuteronomy that
in the day that God created the world, it was from one
end of the heavens to the other. כיוון שסרח, Kevan shesarach, הניח
הקדוש ברוך הוא ידו עליו ומיעטו. heniach Hakadosh Baruch Hu yado alav
umi'ato. When he sinned, God put his hand on him and shrunk
him. And this is in my mind such a beautiful picture. When
Adam sinned, God put his hand on him, it's like God just
like shrunk him, basically, just like pfft. But
think about another piece of this imagery that we're not stopping on,
that God has a hand. But God's hand is big enough to
have Adam, who is from one end of the world to the
other, underneath it. And there are explanations that when God creates human
in the image of... God also has a body which is also
crazy like on one hand of course he doesn't have a body
רמב״ם Rambam would just kill me but on the other hand he
can have whatever he wants so maybe he has a body and
then in his hand he shrinks he shrinks the human
we're bringing a פסוק pasuk שנאמר shenemar אחור וקדם צרתני ותשת עלי
כפכה achor vakedem tzartani vatashet alai kapecha you created me and we'll
see in a minute this פסוק pasuk will get quoted again back
and forth or maybe front and east קדם kedem also another word
for east so you know kind of west of east you formed
me and then you placed your palm on me another option אמר
רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar אדם הראשון מן הארץ עד לרקיע היה
Adam HaRishon min ha'aretz ad larakia haya so the first measurement was
depends where you think the width and the height is but one
measurement was this way and one measurement now is that way okay
מן הארץ עד לרקיע היה min ha'aretz ad larakia haya שנאמר shenemar
למן היום אשר ברא אלוהים אדם על הארץ ומקצה השמים עד קצה
השמים lemin hayom asher bara Elohim Adam al ha'aretz umiktze hashamayim ad
ktze hashamayim God again created human from one end to the other
כיוון שסרח keivan shesarach when he sinned הניח הקדוש ברוך הוא ידו
עליו ומיעטו heniach Hakadosh Baruch Hu yado alav umiyato he shrank him
and we used the same פסוק pasuk שנאמר shenemar אחור וקדם צרתני
achor vakedem tzartani etcetera קשו kashu קאי אהדדי אידי ואידי חדא מידה
היא
kai ahaddi idi ve'idi chada
mida hi like what you're using the same פסוק pasuk in order
to say different things yes it doesn't matter it doesn't matter to
us if the measurement was going this way or that way one
way or another we're trying to say אדם Adam was incredibly big
and then
shrunk ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav I
love this
אדם הראשון בלשון ארמי סיפר Adam HaRishon bilshon Arami siper this is
this what do you call it mnemonic thing so the word ארמי
Arami the first human he spoke Aramaic of course שנאמר
shenemar ולי מה יקרו רעיך אל velei ma yakru re'echa El so
now this is a פסוק pasuk I think תהילים Tehillim yes and
we can explain it in Hebrew your friends your רעים re'im are
dear to me or in Aramaic יקר yakar weighty weight from heavy
כבד kaved רעיך re'echa another word for thoughts so your thoughts are
really like in the sense hard for me difficult you'll see you'll
see in a minute why והיינו דאמר ריש לקיש vehainu de'amar Reish
Lakish ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says מאי דכתיב what does it mean
זה ספר תולדות אדם ze sefer toldot Adam we have a פסוק
pasuk that says this is the book of the generations of Adam
מלמד שהראהו הקדוש ברוך הוא דור דור ודורשיו דור דור וחכמיו melamed
sheher'ahu Hakadosh Baruch Hu dor dor vedorshav dor dor vachachamav the Holy
One Blessed Be He was sitting with אדם Adam they were reading
a bedtime story and God told אדם Adam everything that's coming every
generation and his and its
teachers every generation and its sages כיוון שהגיע לדורו של רבי עקיבא
שמח בתורתו ונתעצב במיתתו
keivan shehigia ledoro shel
Rabbi Akiva samach betorato venitatzev bemitato when אדם Adam got in the
story right in the plot to the generation of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva he was very happy with the תורה Torah that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva brings forth and we know it's from other places but
he was very sad in his death and that's when he said
ולי מה יקרו רעיך אל velei ma yakru re'echa El
like
the way you think השם is
weighty
is heavy on me it's hard for me to understand all right
now we're going completely like kind of off the deep end ואמר
רב יהודה אמר רב ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav יוסי Yosi you'll
bear with me five minutes to finish okay thank you רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of רב אדם הראשון מין
היה Adam HaRishon min haya the first human being was actually an
epicurus how do we know this שנאמר shenemar ויקרא השם אלוהים אל
האדם ויאמר לו איכה vayikra Hashem Elohim el ha'Adam vayomer lo ayeka
God called to the human and he said and he said to
him איכה ayeka this is again like in a whatever we can
stand here and talk about it forever what is the meaning of
God asking אדם Adam where are you like God clearly knows where
he is right if he knows everything he knows where אדם Adam
is so the גמרא Gemara tells us what God really is saying
אן נטה לבך an nata libcha where has your heart wandered to
and from that little word the understanding is that he was not
anymore focused like when God had to stop אדם Adam and say
where are you it's not a physical thing oh I'm on my
way to the store what do you need me to get it's
a what what like would you mind go where where is your
attention and from this little thing that his attention wandered the sages
understand Already there was a split in his mind, already he did
not see the oneness of God, but something, something leaked in. That
gets better.
רבי יצחק אמר מושך בערלתו היה. Rabbi Yitzchak amar moshech beorlato haya.
How do they know that he was a מין, min, how do
they know he was an אפיקורוס? apikores? Because he was playing with
his foreskin. Foreskin, forgive the image.
It's as if, okay, so what is, what is the גמרא Gemara
trying to tell us? Adam was created perfect. We are created not
perfect, and then we have to do things in order to complete
our perfection. Adam is created perfect, therefore the understanding is that he
was created circumcised. How do they know that he's an אפיקורוס? apikores?
He's starting to, like, play with his foreskin to hide his circumcision.
This is, you know, whatever,
the subtext of the subtext. כתיב, Ktiv, now we're going to contrast
two verses. והמה כאדם עברו ברית. vehema keadam avru brit. So we
have one פסוק that says they are like a human that, you
can say, went through a ברית brit or they transgresses the ברית.
brit. וכתיב התם את בריתי הפר, uchtiv hatam et briti hefer, he
transgressed, right, he, what, הפר, hefer,
undid my covenant.
רב
נחמן Rav Nachman takes it further. אמר כופר בעיקר היה. amar kofer
beikar haya.
He was an אפיקורוס apikores that he didn't believe, like, the main
main thing of faith. כתיב, Ktiv, same thing. כתיב הכא, ktiv hacha,
here, עברו ברית, avru brit, וכתיב התם את בריתי הפר, uchtiv hatam
et briti hefer, ואמרו על אשר עזבו את ברית השם. veamru al
asher azvu et brit Hashem. So they're bringing us the פסוקים psukim
that have to do with transgressing the covenant in conjunction with the
word אדם, Adam, we understand from it that אדם Adam already had
some of these doubts about the covenant with God. That reminds us,
this is now the גמרא speaking. If we're already talking about אפיקורסים,
apikorsim, let me tell you some other lessons of or teachings about
us dealing with the אפיקורסים. apikorsim. תנן התם, tnan hatam, it's also
been said. רבי אלעזר אומר הוי שקוד ללמוד תורה ודע מה שתשיב
לאפיקורוס. Rabbi Elazar omer hevei shakud lilmod Torah veda ma shetashiv leapikores.
That should be from פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. So be studious, diligent,
to study תורה Torah and know what you will answer to, how
you will respond to an אפיקורוס. apikores. So there is a commentary
somewhere that דוקא davka תורה, Torah, the point is learn to study
תורה Torah because the אפיקורוס apikores anyway doesn't believe in the תורה
שבעל פה, Torah sheba'al peh, in the oral tradition. So don't bother
with that, but learn the תורה Torah really good so that you
will know how to answer things. אמר רבי יוחנן לא שנו אלא
אפיקורוס של עובדי כוכבים אבל אפיקורוס של ישראל כל שכן דפקר טפי
טפי.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan
lo shna ela apikores shel ovdei kochavim aval apikores shel Yisrael kol
sheken depakir tfei tfei. So it says it doesn't matters less the
אפיקורוס, apikores, the non-believer of the idolaters, but the אפיקורוס apikores that
comes from within the people of ישראל is more אפיקורוס, apikores, is
like more argumentative or, because why? And we'll see in a minute.
Because he knows already all the answers you're going to bring him.
He came to the same classes and he learned the same material
and he decided against it. So you better be ready how to
talk to
them. אמר רבי יוחנן כל מקום שפקרו המינים תשובתם בצדם. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan kol makom shepakru haminin tsuvatam betsidam. Rabbi Yochanan says look at
the text very carefully when you study the תורה Torah and you'll
see many places. He says כל מקום, kol makom, we'll see one
problematic, but many places that the אפיקורוסים apikorsim are using
in order to say, "Eh eh eh, look what's happening here." We'll
see some examples in a minute. The answer is right next to
them. For example, נעשה אדם בצלמנו, na'aseh Adam betsalmenu, let, let us
make man in our image, right? God talks in a plural and
immediately after it says ויברא אלוהים את האדם בצלמו. vayivra Elohim et
haadam betsalmo. And God created the human in his own image. So
it goes between the plural and the singular. הבה נרדה ונבלה שם
שפתם, hava nerda venavla sham sfatam, let us, let us go down
and mix up our language. Us. וירד השם לראות את העיר ואת
המגדל. vayered Hashem lirot et hair ve'et hamigdal. But השם went down
to see the city and the tower. כי שם נגלו אליו האלוהים.
ki sham niglu elav haelohim. For there God plural, gods were
revealed. The whole thing that the word אלוהים, Elohim, which is the
name we call God, is in the plural, should also be, you
know, a whole course taught on these kind of פסוקים. psukim. Okay,
that, that again, that tension. לאל העונה אותי ביום צרתי. la'el ha'oneh
oti beyom tsarati. So the God who answers me in my day
of
trouble. בכל קראנו אליו bechol koreinu eilav them, right, so
he is אלוהים Elohim קרובים kerovim plural אליו elav כהשם אלוהינו בכל
קראנו אליו. kashem Elokeinu bechol koreinu eilav. ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד
בארץ אשר הלכו אלוהים לפדות לו לעם. umi ke'amcha Yisrael goy echad
ba'aretz asher halchu Elohim lifdot lo le'am. And now I will bring
in Daniel. עד די כרסוון ad di chorsevan not sure how to
pronounce from map ועתיק יומין יתיב. ve'atik yomin yetiv. So the again
there is a tension between the plural of the seats and the
יתיב yetiv ישב yeshev in the singular.
הנח למה לי hanach lama li כדרבי יוחנן kiderabbi Yochanan דאמר רבי
יוחנן de'amar rabbi Yochanan אין הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה דבר אלא אם
כן נמלך בפמליא של מעלה. ein hakadosh baruch hu oseh davar ela
im ken nimlach bepamalya shel ma'ala. Rabbi
Yochanan says it is not a problem. All these things are not
a problem. God does not do anything unless he
consults the angels on high שנאמר shenemar בגזירת עירין פתגמא ובמאמר קדישין
שאלתא. begezirat irin pitgama uvema'amar kadishin she'elta. This is what it says
to us in a
פסוק from Daniel that God consults the פמליא של מעלה pamalya shel
ma'ala the angels on high. And they say this was good until
now but now we have a problem with the last saying because
this until now we talked about השם's actions but now we are
talking about chairs.
Okay, so when he is doing things we can say okay he
can be everywhere at the same time but now we are talking
about these chairs, these כרסוון chorsevan like a כורסא kursa like a
couch. Huh?
Throne. How can there be two?
So we have different
explanation. מאי איכא למימר mai ika lemeimar אחד לו ואחד לדוד. echad
lo ve'echad leDavid. One for him, one for the Messiah. דתניא detanya
אחד לו ואחד לדוד echad lo ve'echad leDavid דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei
rabbi Akiva. This is the opinion of Rabbi Akiva that says the
two thrones in the heaven, one for השם and one for David.
Super interesting also beyond what we can do today is Rabbi Akiva's
strong belief in בר כוכבא Bar Kochba as the משיח right? So
like for Rabbi Akiva the משיח is a real is a real
thing that has a throne. אמר לו רבי יוסי amar lo rabbi
Yose עקיבא עד מתי אתה עושה שכינה חול. Akiva ad matai ata
oseh shechina chol. Akiva for how long are you going to make
the שכינה shechina the holy one mundane חול? chol? That is not
the right explanation אלא ela אחד לדין ואחד לצדקה echad ledin ve'echad
letzedaka
one should be to justice and one should be for צדקה tzedaka
for righteousness. So the גמרא is asking how did that conversation go?
קבלה מיניה או לא קבלה מיניה? kabla minei o lo kabla minei?
Did Akiva accept this or did not accept it? תא שמע ta
shema finding in another place דתניא detanya אחד לדין ואחד לצדקה echad
ledin ve'echad letzedaka דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei rabbi Akiva. We find somewhere
else that Rabbi Akiva agrees one for justice one for צדקה. tzedaka.
אמר לו רב אלעזר בן עזריה amar lo rav Elazar ben Azaria
so beautiful like their their friendly conversations right? עקיבא מה לך אצל
הגדה? Akiva ma lecha etzel aggada? Akiva what are you messing around
with אגדתא aggadata right?
כלך אצל נגעים ואהלות. kelach etzel nega'im ve'ohalot. Go go to your
purity and impurity business that you are a genius in. אלא ela
אחד לכיסא ואחד לשרפרף. echad lekise ve'echad leshrafraf. Really the way to
understand it is one is for the throne and one is for
the footstool. When השם sits down at the end of a hard
day of work he sits on the chair and he puts his
feet up on the stool.
כיסא לשבת עליו kise lashevet alav chair to sit שרפרף להדום רגליו
shrafraf lehadom raglav a stool for his feet.
אמר רב נחמן amar rav Nachman since we are talking about all
these Epicuruses reminds us of something else. Rabbi Nachman said האי מן
דידע לאהדורי למינים כרב אידי ליהדר ואי לא לא ליהדר. hai man
deyada le'ahadori leminim kerav Idi leihadar ve'i lo lo leihadar. Rabbi Nachman
tells us no one knew how to respond to the Epicuruses like
Rav Idi. He knew how to give the right response and if
you do not know to respond like him do not. And now
we are going to go into a whole section including the next
page of conversations that our rabbis have with the מינים. minim. Do
we want a little more or pause here and pick it up
tomorrow? Being 8:29-ish. It is 8:38 yeah 8:40. So
where are we?
We are בסוף עמוד ב. besof amud bet.
Yeah are we doing the next דף also? You doing tomorrow? Yeah.
All right that is why I have talked with the person who
is doing tomorrow so I can talk to them again this afternoon.
I mean I can go a little further.
Set that that that.
You so yes? Is that a yes?
Yes we thought we will
go to the next.
Okay, אמר ההוא
מינא לרב אידית *Amar ha-hu mina le-Rav
Idit*. So now we’re going to find challenges that the אפיקורסות *epikorsus*
put to the Rabbis. The first one is a מין *min* to
רב אידית *Rav Idit*. כתיב *ktiv*—I love this—it’s like these אפיקורסות *epikorsus*
are really good in text study. Okay, כתיב *ktiv*, ואל משה אמר
*Ve-el Moshe amar*, God says to Moshe, עלה אל ה' *Aleh el
Hashem*. God says to Moshe come up to Hashem. עלה אלי מיבעי
ליה *Alei elai mibaye leh*—it should have said that Hashem says come
to me, מיבעי ליה *mibaye leh*, right? Like if I say I
will not say whatever Jenna come to Michal, right? I will say
come to me. Why is Hashem talking in the third person? עלה
אלי מיבעי ליה *Alei elai mibaye leh*. אמר לו *Amar lo*, זהו
מטטרון *zehu Metatron* ששמו כשם רבו *she-shmo ke-shem rabo*, דכתיב כי שמי
בקרבו *de-chtiv ki shmi be-kirbo*. Just when you thought this could be
fast. So
מטטרון
*Metatron* has also a גימטריא *gematria*. I will give it so that
we don't spend a lot of time on it. The גימטריא *gematria*
of מטטרון *Metatron* is 314, and that equals the גימטריא *gematria* of
שדי *Shaddai*, שין דלת יוד *Shin Dalet Yud*. So here, בבקשה *bevakasha*,
we can follow the
like Satan, right, like the evil
angel because it's also interesting because we call Hashem Hashem, right, the
name. So they have an identical
name. We're supposed to follow him.
And the פסוק *pasuk* says, כי שמי בקרבו *ki shmi be-kirbo*, my
name is in him. אי הכי נפלחו ליה *Ihachi niflahu leh*—maybe we
should worship him if so, if this is the name. We contrast
it with another פסוק *pasuk*, כתיב אל תמר בו *ktiv al tamer
bo*, don’t defy him, and this is in Exodus 23.
Now the Rabbis change this תמר *tamer*. One option for this שורש
*shoresh* is defy, and then they say אל תמירני בו *al temireni
bo*, don’t replace me with him. But this תמר *tamer* really means
replace and not defy. אם כן לא ישא לפשעכם למה לי *Im
ken lo yissa le-fish'achem lama li*? Like why do I need the
rest of the פסוק *pasuk* that he will not carry our sins?
אמר לו *Amar lo*, הימנותא בידן ואפילו בפרבנקא נמי לא קבליניה *haymanuta
beyadan ve-afillu be-farvanka nami lo kablinei*. We, we are so strong against
מטטרון
*Metatron* that we even as a guide don't accept him. Not only
we don't accept him as a God that makes decisions and carries
our sins, but even as a guide along the way. As it
is written that Moshe says to Hashem, אם אין פניך הולכים *Im
ein panecha holchim*, if your face, if you yourself is not going
with us, then we are not going at all. So we, we
want Hashem. אמר ליה ההוא מינא לרבי ישמעאל *Amar leh ha-hu mina
le-Rabbi Yishmael*, continuing with the אפיקורסות *epikorsus*, this מין *min* said to
Rabbi Yishmael דאמר רבי יוסי *de-Rabbi Yosi*. כתיב *ktiv*: וה' המטיר על
סדום ועל עמורה גופרית ואש מאת ה' *Ve-Hashem himtir al Sedom ve-al
Amora gofrit va-esh me-et Hashem*. Kind of similar. God showered, rained on
סדום *Sedom* and עמורה *Amora* ashes and fire from Hashem. מאתו מיבעי
ליה *me-ito mibaye leh*—it should have said that he showered it from
him. אמר לו *Amar lo*, ההוא כובס *ha-hu koves*, שבקיה אנא מהדרנא
ליה *shavkiya ana mehadrena leh*. So this כובס *koves* says to Rabbi
Yishmael, sit, don’t worry about it, I will respond. And now we
have this כובס *koves*, which is also beautiful. Think about all these
situations. And he says: דכתיב *de-chtiv*, ויאמר למך לנשיו עדה וצלה שמען
קולי נשי למך *Vayomer Lemech le-nashav Ada ve-Tzila sheman koli neshei Lemech*.
So למך *Lemech* in
Genesis says to his wives עדה וצלה *Ada ve-Tzila*, listen to my
voice, the wives of למך *Lemech*. It should have said my wives,
right? נשיי מיבעי ליה *neshai mibaye leh*. אלא משתעי קרא הכי הכא
נמי משתעי קרא הכי *Ela mishtaye kra hachi hacha nami mishtaye kra
hachi*. This is how the Torah speaks, and that is we accept
that that is the language of the text. ורבי ישמעאל *Ve-Rabbi Yishmael*
is impressed from this כובס *koves* that can answer. אמר לו *Amar
lo*, מנלך *minalach*? How do you know this? He says, הא מפרקי
דרבי מאיר שמיע לי *Ha mi-pirkei de-Rabbi Meir shmiya li*. This, this
is I’ve heard these teachings from רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. דאמר רבי
יוחנן *de-amar Rabbi Yochanan*, כי הוה דריש רבי מאיר בפרקיה הוה דריש
תילתא שמעתא *ki hava drish Rabbi Meir be-pirkei hava drish tilta shamata*—a
third of his teachings רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* were in הלכה *halakha*—תילתא
אגדתא *tilta aggadata*—in אגדתא *aggadata*—ותילתא מתלי *ve-tilta matlei*, משלים *meshalim*, parables. ואמר
רבי יוחנן *ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan*, ג' מאות *gimmel me'ot*, 300, שלוש מאות
משלי שועלים היו לו לרבי מאיר *shlosh me'ot mashal shu'alim hayu lo
le-Rabbi Meir*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* had 300
fox parables. Rabbi Meir was so rich in parables, he had three
hundred parables that had to do with foxes, ואנו and we אין
לנו אלא שלוש ein lanu ela shalosh we only have three parables
about foxes and the fox parables that are waiting for us in
suspense we're going to open with the morning tomorrow. It's a fun
parable and I look forward to continuing bright and early.
All right, thank you everyone here and far. Now let's try to
push
that
button.